# NICOLÒ DAL FABBRO

n.dalfabbro@gmail.com https://ndf96.github.io Philadelphia, PA, USA

Ph.D. in Information and Communication Technology. Currently a postdoctoral researcher at the University of Pennsylvania, USA. My research interest is mainly in the analysis and design of multi-agent and distributed machine learning algorithms, with a focus on wireless communications and sensing.

#### **EDUCATION**

## PHD, INFORMATION AND COMMUNICATION TECHNOLOGY

Department of Information Engineering, University of Padova, Italy | October 2020 - October 2023

# VISITING PHD STUDENT, GRASP (General Robotics, Automation, Sensing, and Perception)

Electrical and Systems Engineernig, University of Pennsylvania, USA | September 2022 - April 2023

## M. S., TELECOMMUNICATIONS ENGINEERING

Department of Information Engineering, University of Padova, Italy | 2018 - 2020

## **EXCHANGE STUDENT, Swiss European Mobility Program (SEMP) (Scholarship Recipient)**

École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL), School of Computer and Communication Sciences, Switzerland | 2019 - 2020

#### **B. S. IN INFORMATION ENGINEERING**

University of Padova, Italy | 2015 - 2018

## **WORK EXPERIENCE**

# POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER

Electrical and Systems Engineering, University of Pennsylvania, USA | November 2023 - Current

• Conducting research in Federated Learning and Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning with applications in autonomous driving and underwater robotics.

#### UNIVERSITY RESEARCH ASSISTANT

University of Padova, Padova, Italy | September 2020 – September 2023

• Research on algorithm design for Federated Learning in the context of wireless 5G/6G networks, theoretical analysis of distributed and multi-agent reinforcement learning algorithms.

## **UNIVERSITY TEACHING ASSISTANT, Numerical Calculus**

Department of Mathematics, University of Padova, Italy | February 2022 – July 2022

• Conducting practical sessions with excercises on numerical calculus in Matlab

## RESEARCH INTERN, SIGNET RESEARCH GROUP, DEI

University of Padova, Italy | February 2020 - August 2020

• Experimental research on WiFi-based human sensing

## **SKILLS**

#### **Programming Languages and Software**

Python | MATLAB | C++ | LaTeX | Linux | Github | Slack

# Multilingual

Italian (native) | English (fluent) | French (basic)

## **AWARDS**

- Best PhD Thesis Award, by the Italian Telecommunications and Information Technology Group (GTTI) for the year 2024: http://www.gtti.it/awards/
- Winner of the Fall 2022 IEEE DataPort Dataset Upload Contest in the Machine Learning category based on unique dataset views as measured by Google Analytics and a review from a committee of the IEEE (https://ieee-dataport.org/documents/csi-dataset-wireless-human-sensing-80-mhz-wi-fi-channels)

# **PUBLICATIONS**

N. Dal Fabbro, M. Rossi, G. Pillonetto, L. Schenato, and G. Piro. **Model-Free Radio Map Estimation in Massive MIMO Systems via Semi-Parametric Gaussian Regression.** *IEEE Wireless Communications Letters*, 2022, doi: 10.1109/LWC.2021.3132458

N. Dal Fabbro, S. Dey, M. Rossi, and L. Schenato. **SHED: A Newton-Type Algorithm for Federated Learning based on Incremental Hessian Eigenvector Sharing.** *Automatica*, 2024, doi: 10.1016/j.automatica.2023.111460

F. Meneghello, D. Garlisi, N. Dal Fabbro, I. Tinnirello, and M. Rossi. **SHARP: Environment and Person Independent Activity Recognition with Commodity IEEE 802.11 Access Points**. *IEEE Transactions on Mobile Computing*, 2022, doi: 10.1109/TMC.2022.3185681

F. Meneghello, N. Dal Fabbro, D. Garlisi, I. Tinnirello, and M. Rossi. **A CSI Dataset for Wireless Human Sensing on 80 MHz Wi-Fi Channels**. *IEEE Communications Magazine*, 2023, doi: 10.1109/MCOM.005.2200720

N. Dal Fabbro, A. Mitra, and G. J. Pappas. **Federated TD Learning over Finite-Rate Erasure Channels: Linear Speedup under Markovian Sampling.** *IEEE Control Systems Letters*, 2023 doi: 10.1109/LCSYS.2023.3287499 (also accepted and presented at the 62nd IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC 2023)

N. Dal Fabbro, M. Rossi, L. Schenato, and S. Dey. **Q-SHED: Distributed Optimization at the Edge via Hessian Eigenvectors Quantization.** *IEEE International Conference on Communications (ICC)*, Rome, Italy, 2023, doi: 10.1109/ICC45041.2023.10279510

N. Dal Fabbro, A. Mitra, R. W. Heath, L. Schenato, and G. J. Pappas. **Over-the-Air Federated TD Learning**. *Sixth Conference on Machine Learning and Systems (MLSys23)*, Workshop on Resource-Constrained Learning in Wireless Networks, Miami, Florida, 2023

Arman Adibi, Nicolò Dal Fabbro, Luca Schenato, Sanjeev Kulkarni, H. Vincent Poor, George J. Pappas, Hamed Hassani and Aritra Mitra. **Stochastic Approximation with Delayed Updates: Finite-Time Rates under Markovian Sampling**, *The 27th International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS)*, Valencia, Spain, 2024, https://proceedings.mlr.press/v238/adibi24a

Luca Ballotta, Nicolò Dal Fabbro, Giovanni Perin, Luca Schenato, Michele Rossi, Giuseppe Piro. **VREM-FL: Mobility-Aware Computation-Scheduling Co-Design for Vehicular Federated Learning**, accepted for publication, *IEEE Transactions on Vehicular Technology*, 202x, preprint available arXiv:2311.18741

Andrea Agiollo, Enkeleda Bardhi, Mauro Conti, Nicolò Dal Fabbro, Riccardo Lazzeretti. **Anonymous Federated Learning via Named-Data Networking**, Future Generation Computer Systems, 2024, doi: 10.1016/j.future.2023.11.009

Nicolò Dal Fabbro, Arman Adibi, Aritra Mitra, George J. Pappas. **Finite-Time Analysis of Asynchronous Multi-Agent TD Learning**, *The 2024 American Control Conference (ACC)*, 2024

Nicolò Dal Fabbro, Arman Adibi, Aritra Mitra, George J. Pappas. **DASA: Delay-Adaptive Multi-Agent Stochastic Approximation**, Accepted for publication, 62nd IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC), 2024

## ADDITIONAL EXPERIENCE AND VOLUNTEERING

- Organizing weekly meetings between group members of Prof. George Pappas research group at the University of Pennsylvania. I have been organizing the meetings with the main objective of spurring collaboration, stimulating knowledge exchange and networking
- Attended and actively contributed to prestigious international PhD schools, including the IEEE/DEI Summer PhD School of Information Engineering "Silvano Pupolin" – SSIE 2022 (<a href="https://ssie.dei.unipd.it/">https://ssie.dei.unipd.it/</a>), and the 5G International PhD School, December 2020 (<a href="https://www.5gitaly.eu/2020/">https://www.5gitaly.eu/2020/</a>)
- Reviewer for esteemed international journals, such as Signal Processing (Elsevier), Automatica (Elsevier), Transactions on Mobile Computing (IEEE), Transactions on Vehicular Technology (IEEE) since 2021
- Co-founded and actively participated in Venice Calls (https://www.venicecalls.com/), a non-profit organization of social promotion in Venice. Helped coordinate volunteers during the 2019 flooding crisis, providing assistance to affected citizens, institutions, and businesses (https://www.festivalitaca.net/2020/02/venice-calls-gli-angeli-veneziani-dellacqua-alta/). Organized public events, including conferences and clean-up initiatives in the Venice Lagoon. Contributed to promoting public participation and cultural events.